all right
[Music]
our lifetime risk of developing an
invasive cancer not like some
superficial skin cancer like ductal
carcinoma the breast but serious cancer
is about 40 percent two in five of us
are going to get a cancer diagnosis in
our lifetimes
what can we do to reduce our risk only
about five percent of cancers are caused
by problem genes we inherited from our
parents the other 95 are caused by
mutations in our DNA we acquire in our
lifetimes for example based on a genetic
analysis of lung cancer smokers May
acquire an average of one DNA mutation
for every 15 cigarettes smoked smoking
is bad but the number one cause of these
mutations is our diet and that's not
even including the cancers attributed to
obesity
I've got tons of videos
on dietary approaches to prevent cancer
but what if you already have it
well-meaning professionals sometimes
counsel cancer patients that eat
whatever you want right given the time
constraints that doctors face Maybe
understandable that the treating
oncologists the the treating cancer
doctor may be reluctant to engage in a
conversation about nutrition but given
the critical role that diet may play
perhaps it should be a critical part of
their job to be able to answer patients
questions about nutrition before and
after cancer treatment and not default
to the unhelpful it doesn't really
matter eat whatever you want which may
not be in the best interest of the
patient the official recommendation of
the American Institute of cancer
research leading Authority on dying
cancer is that those with cancer should
follow the same diet that helps prevent
cancer from taking root in the first
place that means
more whole grains vegetables fruits and
beans while limiting fast food processed
food meat soda and alcohol
similar recommendations have been put
forth by other cancer authorities more
fruit vegetables whole grains and beans
and less salt sugar meat and alcohol
cancer survivors adhering to these
guidelines do seem to live significantly
longer at least older female cancer
survivors the only group in which it's
been looked at so far
they had that there are certain foods
that may be beneficial in Cancer Care
including beans berries cruciferous
vegetables flaxseed garlic green tea
tomatoes and others but you know
emphasize it's not about a single Magic
Bullet food or component but the
combination of foods in a predominantly
plant-based diet
here's how some popular diets used by
cancer patients stack up the so-called
alkaline diet gets high marks for being
vegetable focused and encouraging people
to cut down on animal Foods the keto
diet does the worst though they get
points for keeping people away from
refined grains alcohol and soft drinks
macrobiotic diets you really kind of win
the day being closest to a whole food
plant-based I centered around whole
grains vegetables and beans though may
not be advising enough fruit
paleo diets are a mixed bag with
insufficient whole grains and beans and
too much meat and the vegan diet starts
out strong but doesn't necessarily
preclude all manner of vegan junk food
have any of these diets been put to the
test I've done a video on the abject
failure of the keto diet the alkaline
diet was tried on 11 lung cancer
patients they lived an average of 20 and
a half months which is about 40 percent
longer than most patients have
historically lived but there was no
direct control group the only diet
proven in a randomized control trial to
reverse the progression of cancer
was Dr Dean Orange's Whole Food
plant-based lifestyle program which I've
covered before most randomized
controlled trials to data and diet and
cancer are like this right feasibility
studies just to see if like you can even
get cancer patients to eat healthier
period otherwise what's the point of
even running the study here they did
fine they could get patients with head
and neck cancer to ramp up green leafy
and cruciferous vegetable intake up to
nine cups a week so it's at least
something you could test we don't yet
have outcomes data but look why wait
what's the downside of trying to eat
healthier
it may even save your life another way
cardiovascular disease competes with
breast cancer as the leading cause of
death for older women diagnosed with
breast cancer researchers fall more than
60 000 women diagnosed with breast
cancer over the age of 65. for an
average of nine years by which time half
had died and the number one cause of
death was actually cardiovascular
disease edging out the breast cancer and
so choosing a healthy diet centered
around whole plant Foods the only diet
ever proven to reverse heart disease in
the majority of patients May save your
life whether you have cancer
or not
[Music]